A Guide to the Fenwick Civil War Materials Collection c.1863-1865
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Fenwick Civil War Materials Collection c. 1863-1865
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Ms2001-042
1 container; .2 cu. ft.
A small collection of Civil War-related materials, containing the correspondence of John Newton Smith, a private in Company I, 13th Virginia Cavalry and the sketchbook of Charles Gulager, a private in Company A, 6th Pennsylvania Cavalry.
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Fenwick Collection was donated to Special Collections at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University in 2000. The Gulager sketchbook had been inherited by Mr. Fenwick; Smith's letters had belonged to Mrs. Fenwick.
Biographical/Historical Information
John Newton Smith, a Confederate cavalryman, was born in Nansemond County, Virginia on March 5, 1843. He was the oldest child of Burwell Riddick and Sarah Marie Cross. On June 4, 1861, "Newt" Smith enlisted at Suffolk in what would eventually become Company I of the 13th Virginia Cavalry. Smith died from typhoid fever at Hanover Courthouse military hospital (Virginia) on June 9, 1863.
Charles Gulager, an artist and Union cavalryman, was born on August 7, 1826. Best known for his paintings of naval and coastal subjects, Gulager lived in Philadelphia prior to the Civil War, and his paintings were exhibited at the Pennsylvania Academy in 1860. During the Civil War, Gulager was a private in Company A, 6th Pennsylvania Cavalry. He died on December 1, 1898, and is buried in Oakwood Cemetery, Falls Church, Virginia.
Sources
Balfour, Daniel T., 13th Virginia Cavalry (Lynchburg, VA: H. E. Howard, 1986).
Groce, George C. and David H. Wallace, The New-York Historical Society's Dictionary of Artists in America, 1564-1860 (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1957).
Miltier, Kelly, comp. "Tom Smith Camp: the Family of Thomas Washington Smith." http://www.tomsmithcamp.com/genealogy/ (25 July 2002).
Scope and Content Information
This collection contains Civil War materials which had been inherited by Edward G. and Dorothea Little Vanderslice Fenwick. The collection is divided into two series: the Charles Gulager sketchbook and the John Newton Smith correspondence.
The Charles Gulager sketchbook (measuring approximately 5 x 7 inches) contains more than 30 sketches drawn by Gulager while he served in Company A of the 6th Pennsylvania Cavalry. Many of the sketches depict war-related scenes, such as camps, soldiers and ships. Also among the sketches are illustrations of such historic structures as Mount Vernon and the Chain Bridge at Washington, D. C. (Selections from the sketchbook were published by Mr. Fenwick in 1987 under the title The Civil War Sketches of Charles Gulager [call number: NC139.G85 A4 1987 Civil War Spec]). The sketches may also be viewed by searching "Gulager" on Special Collections' ImageBase (http://imagebase.lib.vt.edu/). While many of the sketches are titled, some are either untitled or have titles which are illegible.
The John Newton Smith correspondence contains letters written by Smith while serving with Company I, 13th Virginia Cavalry. The letters span the first half of 1863 and are written mostly from Essex County, as well as other points in northeastern Virginia. Smith's letters are devoted largely to personal matters (especially his need for a hat, the illness and death of his horse, war-time prices and family affairs), but he also writes of military matters (especially the Chancellorsville campaign). The correspondence concludes with letters from Smith's cousin, Charles Croft, regarding Smith's severe illness and subsequent death, as well as documents related to the military pay due Smith's estate. The series also contains a set of transcriptions made-probably in the early twentieth century-from the original letters.
Organization
Charles Gulager Sketchbook, c.1861-1865: This series contains a sketchbook kept by Gulager during the Civil War. The sketchbook is self-contained, and the illustrations are arranged in no particular order.
John Newton Smith Letters, 1863-1864: This series contains letters written by Smith from various points in northeastern Virginia during the first half of 1863. It also contains letters from Charles Croft regarding Smith's illness and death, as well as official communications regarding the military pay due Smith's estate. The letters, which are arranged chronologically, are followed by a set of transcriptions, also arranged by date of original letter.
Index Terms
Persons:
Gulager, Charles; Smith, John Newton
Subjects:
Civil War; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865
Contents List
- Charles Gulager Sketchbook c.1861-1865
  - Sketchbook c.1861-1865 (Box-folder Box-folder: 1-1)
- John Newton Smith Letters 1863-1864
  - To "Pa"-Headquarters, Lee's Cavalry Brigade, Jan 11, 1863 (Box-folder Box-folder: 1-2)
  - To "Sister"-Headquarters, Lee's Cavalry Brigade, Jan 11, 1863 (Box-folder Box-folder: 1-2)
  - To "Brother"-Headquarters, Lee's Cavalry Brigade, Jan 15, 1863 (Box-folder Box-folder: 1-2)
  - To "Pa"-Essex Co., Virginia, Jan 21, 1863 (Box-folder Box-folder: 1-2)
  - To "Sister"-Essex Co., Virginia, Feb 1, 1863 (Box-folder Box-folder: 1-2)
  - To "Pa"-Essex Co., Virginia, Feb 9, 1863 (Box-folder Box-folder: 1-2)
  - To "Pa"-Essex Co., Virginia, Feb 15, 1863 (Box-folder Box-folder: 1-2)
  - To "Sister"-Essex Co., Virginia, Feb 20, 1863 (Box-folder Box-folder: 1-2)
  - To "Pa"-Essex Co., Virginia, Feb 25, 1863 (Box-folder Box-folder: 1-2)
  - To "Cousin Ida"-Camp Gregg, Virginia, Apr 1, 1863 (Box-folder Box-folder: 1-2)
  - To "Sister"-Culpepper Court House, Virginia, Apr 12, 1863 (Box-folder Box-folder: 1-2)
  - To "Pa"-Orange Court House, Virginia, May 5, 1863 (Box-folder Box-folder: 1-2)
  - To "Sister"-Orange Court House, Virginia, May 14, 1863 (Box-folder Box-folder: 1-2)
  - To "Uncle" from C.T. Croft-Hanover Academy Hospital, Jun 2, 1863 (Box-folder Box-folder: 1-2)
  - To "Uncle" from Charles Croft-Hanover Academy Hospital, Jun 8, 1863 (Box-folder Box-folder: 1-2)
  - To Estate of John N. Smith from Alex. Savage, Jun 8, 1863 (Box-folder Box-folder: 1-2)
  - To "Uncle" from Charles Croft-Hanover Academy Hospital, Jun 9, 1863 (Box-folder Box-folder: 1-2)
  - To "Sir" from S. Meredith-Hanover Academy Hospital, Sep 29, 1863 (Box-folder Box-folder: 1-2)
  - To B.R. Smith from Capt. A. Savage-Fredericksburg, Virginia, Mar 18, 1864 (Box-folder Box-folder: 1-2)
  - Transcriptions of letters n.d. (Box-folder Box-folder: 1-3)